<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>GST News &amp; Updates</title>
<description><![CDATA[News and updates from the GST Portal]]></description>
<link>https://www.gst.gov.in/</link>
<item>
<pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns,e-Invoice,E-Way Bill] Advisory on RSP-Based Valuation of Notified Tobacco Goods under GST</title>
<description><![CDATA[<p>An advisory on reporting of taxable value and tax liability under RSP-based valuation in e-Invoice, e-Way Bill and GSTR-1 / GSTR-1A / IFF has been issued for the information and guidance of taxpayers. The advisory may be accessed through the link provided below.</p>
 
<a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/advisory_on_rsp_based_valuation_gstr-1_final_version.pdf" target="blank">https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/advisory_on_rsp_based_valuation_gstr-1_final_version.pdf</a> <br> <br>



Thanks, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/646</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Registration] Advisory on Filing Opt-In Declaration for Specified Premises, 2025</title>
<description><![CDATA[
 
<p>Dear Taxpayers,</p>
 
<p>The relevant declarations issued vide Notification No. 05/2025 – Central Tax (Rate), dated 16th January 2025, are now made available electronically on the GST Portal. These declarations may be opted for and filed by persons who are applying for registration or are already registered and supplying hotel accommodation services by declaring the premises as “specified premises”.</p>
 
<p>Kindly take note of the following key points:</p>
 
<p><b>1. Who may opt and file the declaration</b>
<ul> •	Regular taxpayers (active and suspended) supplying hotel accommodation service who want to declare their premises to be a "specified premises"</ul> 
<ul> •	Applicants for new GST registration who want to declare their premises to be a “Specified Premises” </ul> 
The facility is not applicable to composition taxpayers, TDS/TCS taxpayers, SEZ units/developers, casual taxpayers, or cancelled registrations.
</p>
 
<p><b>2. Types of Declarations</b>
<p>The following declarations are made available on the portal:</p>
<ul>1.	Annexure VII: Opt-In Declaration for Registered Person
– For existing registered taxpayers opting to declare premises as specified premises for a succeeding financial year.</ul>
<ul>2.	Annexure VIII: Opt-In Declaration for Person Applying for Registration
– For persons applying for new registration, to declare premises as specified premises from the effective date of registration.</ul>
<p>(Annexure IX – Opt-Out Declaration will be made available separately in due course of time.)</p></p>
 
 
<p><b>3. Timeline for Filing Declarations</b>
<p>(A) Existing Registered Taxpayers – Annexure VII</p>
<ul>•	Can be filed for the subsequent financial year during the specified window: 1st January to 31st March of the preceding financial year.</ul>
<ul>•	For FY 2026-27, Annexure VII can be filed from 01.01.2026 to 31.03.2026.</ul>
<p>(B) New Registration Applicants – Annexure VIII</p>
<ul>•	Can be filed within 15 days from the date of generation of ARN of the registration application.</ul>
<ul>•	Filing is allowed irrespective of whether GSTIN has been allotted, provided the application is not rejected.</ul>
<ul>•	After the lapse of 15 days, the opt-in declaration can be filed only when the window for Annexure VII is available, i.e., 1st January to 31st March.</ul>
<ul>•	Taxpayers will not be able to file Annexure VIII if the registration application is rejected, irrespective of the fact that the 15 days have lapsed or not.</ul></p>
 
 
<p><b>4. How to File the Declaration on GST Portal</b>
<ul> 1.	Log in to the GST Portal</ul> 
<ul> 2.	Navigate to: Services -> Registration -> Declaration for Specified Premises</ul> 
<ul> 3.	Select the appropriate option:
<ul>o	Opt-In Declaration for Specified Premises, or</ul>
<ul>o	Download Annexure Filed</ul></ul>
 
<ul> 4.	Select eligible premises, fill in the declaration, and submit using EVC.</ul>
<p>On successful submission, an ARN will be generated.</p>
</p>
 
<p><b>5. Important Points to Note</b>
<ul>•	A maximum of 10 premises can be selected in one declaration. Additional declarations may be filed for remaining premises, if any. However, separate PDFs with reference numbers will be generated for each premise. </ul>
<ul> •	If any premises are left for opt-in, the taxpayer may again file Annexure VII for that premise for the same financial year during the eligible window period.</ul>
<ul> •	Suspended taxpayers are allowed to file the declaration. However, cancelled taxpayers are barred from filing such declarations.</ul>
<ul>•	The option exercised will continue for subsequent financial years unless an opt-out declaration (Annexure IX) is filed within the prescribed time. </ul></p>
 
 
<p><b>6. Downloading of Filed Declarations</b>
<ul>•	Filed Annexures (VII / VIII) can be downloaded from:
Services -> Registration ->Declaration for Specified Premises -> Download </ul>
<ul>•	Separate reference numbers are generated for each declared premise.</ul></p>
 
<p><b>7. Email and SMS Intimation</b>
 
<ul>•	Confirmation via email and SMS will be sent to all authorised signatories upon successful filing of the declaration. </ul></p>
 
<p><b>Note:</b>
 
<ul>1.	For the first year, i.e., FY 2025–26, these declarations were filed manually with the jurisdictional authority. However, since an online filing facility has now been made available, it is requested that such taxpayers shall file Annexure VII for the specified premises again electronically for <b>FY 2026–27</b> from 1st January 2026 to 31st March 2026.</ul>
<ul>2.	Declaring specified premises for the first time:
Such taxpayers are required to file Annexure VII for<b> FY 2026-27</b> from 1st January 2026 to 31st March 2026.
</ul></p>
 
Thanks, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/645</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Others] Gross and Net GST revenue collections for the month of Dec, 2025</title>
<description><![CDATA[<ul><p>Please click on the link below to view the gross and net GST revenue collections for the month of Dec, 2025.</p></ul>
<ul><p><a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/monthly_gst_data_for_publishing_dec_2025_final_01jan2026.pdf" target="blank">https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/monthly_gst_data_for_publishing_dec_2025_final_01jan2026.pdf</a></p></ul>

Thanks, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/644</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Advisory &amp; FAQ on Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed Statement &amp; RCM Liability/ITC Statement</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>1.&nbsp;	To ensure correct and accurate reporting of reversed and reclaimed ITC and to avoid clerical mistakes, <b><i>Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed Statement (Reclaim Ledger)</i></b> was introduced on the GST portal from <i>August 2023 return period onwards for monthly taxpayers and from July-September 2023 quarter for quarterly taxpayers.</i> This Reclaim Ledger captures the ITC temporarily reversed in Table 4(B)2 and its subsequent reclaim in Table 4(A)5) and 4(D)1. </p>

<p>2.&nbsp;	As of now taxpayer get a <b>warning message</b> if a taxpayer attempts to re-claim excess ITC in table 4D(1) than the available ITC reversal balance but the taxpayer is allowed to file its Form GSTR-3B.</p>

<p>3.&nbsp;	To the taxpayers multiple opportunities have been given to report their opening balance which was earlier reversed ITC but was not reclaimed till that time, for the newly introduced Reclaim Ledger. </p>

<p>4.&nbsp;	This statement can be viewed by the taxpayer by navigating to the <b>Dashboard › Services › Ledger › Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed</b>.</p>

<p>5.&nbsp;	To assist taxpayers in correctly reporting Reverse Charge Mechanism (RCM) transactions, another statement called <b>"RCM Liability/ITC Statement" (RCM Ledger)</b> was introduced on the GST Portal from August 2024 onwards for monthly filers and from July-September-2024 period for quarterly filers. The ledger captures and track the RCM liability shown in Table 3.1(d) of GSTR-3B and its corresponding ITC claimed in Table 4A(2) and 4A(3) of GSTR-3B for each return period. 
</p>

<p>6.&nbsp;	A <b>warning message</b> comes to the taxpayer in case the ITC claimed in Table 4(A)2 and 4(A)3 exceed the closing balance of RCM ledger plus the liabilities being reported in Table 3.1(d).</p>

<p>7.&nbsp;	To the taxpayers multiple opportunities have been given to report the RCM ITC opening balance and amend the opening balance for both the said statements where any transaction related to excess ITC reversal or excess RCM liability/ITC prior to implementation of the said statements could be declared as opening balance to these statements.</p>

<p>8.&nbsp;	This RCM Liability/ITC Statement can be accessed through:<b> Services >> Ledger >> RCM Liability/ITC Statement</b>.</p>

<p>9.&nbsp;	Now, the taxpayers are hereby informed that, shortly, negative values or availment of excess ITC over and above available balance, shall not be allowed in both the ledgers. Both the statements shall have a below mentioned validation for regulation of ITC:  
<ul>a.&nbsp;	The reclaimed ITC in Table 4(D)(1) shall be lesser than or equal to the combined values of closing balance of <b><i>Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed Statement</i></b> and ITC being reversed in Table 4(B)(2) of current period GSTR-3B. and,</ul>
<ul>b.&nbsp;	The RCM ITC claimed in Table 4(A)2 & 4(A)3 shall be equal to or less than the combined values of RCM liabilities paid in Table 3.1(d) of the same GSTR-3B and closing balance of RCM Liability/ITC Statement.</ul></p>

<p>10.&nbsp;	In case the taxpayers are already having negative closing balance in <b><i>Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed Statement or RCM Liability/ITC Statement</b></i>, the system will not allow such taxpayers to file their GSTR-3B until:</p>

<p><ul>a.&nbsp;	Mandatorily reversal of such excess claimed ITC (Negative closing balance) as per <b><i>Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed Statement</b></i> is made in Table 4(B)(2) of current period GSTR-3B. In case there is no ITC available in current period, this reversal declared in table 4(B)2 will be added to the liability of the taxpayer in current period while filing GSTR-3B. </ul></p>

<p><ul>b.&nbsp;	For negative balance in <b><i>RCM Liability/ITC Statement</b></i>, taxpayer need to either pay the additional RCM liability equivalent to negative closing balance in Table 3.1(d) or reduce the ITC claimed in Table 4A(2) or 4A(3) to the extent of closing balance in the current return period.</ul></p>

<p>11.&nbsp;	For more information on <b><i>Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed Statement</b></i> please refer the advisory dated 17th September, 2024 issued by GSTN by clicking below link <a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/itc_pending_ledger.pdf" target="blank">https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/itc_pending_ledger.pdf</a>. Also, detailed advisory on Introduction of RCM Liability/ITC Statement can be seen by clicking on below link:<a href="https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/514" target="blank">https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/514</a> .</p>




 
<p><u><b>FAQs related to Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed Statement and RCM Liability/ITC Statement</b></u></p>

<p><b>1.&nbsp;How to view my Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed Statement?</b></p>


<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;You can view the statement by navigating to the <b>Dashboard</b> &rsaquo; <b>Services</b> &rsaquo; <b>Ledger</b> &rsaquo; <b>Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed.</b></p>

<p><b>2.&nbsp;How to view my RCM Liability/ITC Statement?</b></p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;You can view the RCM Liability/ITC Statement by navigating to the  <b>Dashboard</b> &rsaquo; <b>Services</b> &rsaquo; <b>Ledger</b> &rsaquo; <b>RCM Liability/ITC Statement.</b> </p>

<p><b>3.&nbsp;What will be changed in the GSTR-3B in respect of <i>Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed Statement?</i></b></p>


<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Shortly, taxpayer will not be able to file their GSTR-3B in case the ITC claimed in Table 4D&#40;1&#41; exceeds the closing balance in the <i><b>Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed Statement &#40;ITC reclaim ledger&#41;</i></b> and the ITC reversed in Table 4B&#40;2&#41; of the current return period putting together.</p>


<p><b>4.&nbsp;How to file GSTR-3B if closing balance of Electronic Credit Reversal and Re-claimed Statement &#40;ITC reclaim ledger&#41; is already Negative?</b><p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;If the closing balance of the ITC reclaim ledger is negative, it indicates that excess ITC was reclaimed earlier. Therefore, to file GSTR-3B, you must reverse the excess claimed ITC in Table 4B&#40;2&#41; of the respective return period, up to the amount of the negative closing balance. This will allow you to correct the discrepancy and proceed with filing the return. In case there is no ITC available, this reversal declared in table 4&#40;B&#41;2 will be added to your liability in current period while filing GSTR-3B.</p>

<p><i>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Example: The closing balance of the ITC reclaim ledger for the current return period is -&#8377;10,000, which means &#8377;10,000 of excess ITC has been reclaimed in earlier periods. To file your GSTR-3B, you would need to reverse this earlier excess reclaimed ITC of &#8377;10,000 in Table 4B&#40;2&#41; for the current period.</i></p>

<p><b>5.&nbsp;How will the validation mechanism work in GSTR-3B for RCM Liability/ITC Statement?</b>.<p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;The taxpayers will not be able to file GSTR-3B in case the claimed RCM ITC in Table 4A&#40;2&#41; or 4A&#40;3&#41; exceeds the available balance in the RCM Liability/ITC Statement and the RCM liability reported in Table 3.1&#40;d&#41; for the current return period put together. </p>



<p><b>6.&nbsp;How to file GSTR-3B if closing balance of RCM Liability/ITC Statement is Negative?</b></p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;If the closing balance of the RCM Liability/ITC Statement is negative, it indicates that excess RCM ITC has been claimed earlier. To proceed with filing, you must either pay the outstanding RCM liability in Table 3.1&#40;d&#41; or reduce the ITC being claimed in Table 4A&#40;2&#41; or 4A&#40;3&#41; in the current return period, equivalent the amount of the negative closing balance. Once the discrepancy is corrected, you will be able to file your return.</p>

<p><b>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Example:</b></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Let’s assume that the closing balance of the RCM Liability/ITC Statement is -&#8377;5,000. This means that &#8377;5,000 of excess RCM ITC has been claimed earlier. To resolve this and file your GSTR-3B, you can:</p>

<p><b>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;1.&nbsp;Pay the RCM liability</b>: You can pay additional &#8377;5,000 in Table 3.1&#40;d&#41; for the current return period to cover the excess ITC claimed.</p>
<b>OR</b>
<p><b>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;2.&nbsp;Reduce the ITC claimed</b>: You can reduce &#8377;5,000 from the RCM ITC in Table 4A&#40;2&#41; or Table 4A&#40;3&#41; for the same period, if RCM ITC is available more than &#8377;5,000 in current period.</p>


<p>Once either the excess RCM liability is paid or the requisite ITC is reduced from available ITC to match the available negative closing balance, the discrepancy will be resolved, and you can proceed with filing your return.</p>
 
 
Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/643</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Consolidated FAQs on GSTR -9/9C for FY 2024-25</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>GSTN has published series of FAQ on 16th Oct, 2025 and  4th Dec, 2025 for assisting the taxpayer in filing of Annual Return i.e., GSTR-9/9C.  For convenience, the taxpayer may access Consolidated FAQs by 
<a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/combined_faq_on_gstr_9_and_9c_17122025.pdf" target="blank"">clicking here</a>.</p>
 
Thanking you , <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/642</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Registration] Auto Suspension of GST Registration due to Non-Furnishing of Bank Account Details as per Rule 10A</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><b>Dear Taxpayers,</b></p>

<p>As per Rule 10A, taxpayers (except those registered under TCS, TDS, or Suo-moto registrations) must furnish their bank account details within 30 days of grant of registration or before filing details of outward supplies in GSTR-1 or IFF, whichever is earlier.</p>

<p>The following updates have been implemented on the GST Portal with respect to Rule 10A:</p>

<ul>
<li>Automatic Suspension:</br>
If a taxpayer fails to furnish bank account details within 30 days of registration, the system will automatically suspend the registration. The suspension order can be viewed at: Services > User Services > View Notices and Orders.</li>
</br>
<li>Adding Bank Account Details:</br>
Taxpayers can add bank account details through a non-core amendment by navigating to: Services > Registration > Amendment of Registration (Non-Core Fields).</li>
</br>
<li>Automatic Dropping of Cancellation Proceedings:</br>
Once bank account details are furnished, cancellation proceedings will be automatically dropped by the system.
</li>
</br>
<li>Manual Option to Drop Proceedings:</br>
If the cancellation proceedings are not dropped automatically on the same day after adding bank details, the taxpayer can manually initiate the process using the “Initiate Drop Proceedings” button available at: Services > User Services > View Notices and Orders > Initiate Drop Proceedings.</li>
</br>
<li>Exemptions:</br>
Furnishing bank account details is not mandatory for OIDAR and NRTP taxpayers. However, for OIDAR taxpayers who select “Representative Appointed in India” as ‘Yes’, furnishing bank account details is mandatory.
</li>
</ul></br>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/641</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Advisory on reporting values in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B</title>
<description><![CDATA[
 
<ol>
<li>
<p>Table 3.2 of Form GSTR-3B captures the inter-state supplies made to unregistered persons, composition taxpayers, and UIN holders out of the total supplies declared in Table 3.1 & 3.1.1 of GSTR-3B and is auto-populated from corresponding supplies declared in GSTR-1, GSTR-1A, and IFF in the requisite tables.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>It is to inform you that from <b>November-2025 tax period onwards</b>, value of supplies auto-populated in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B from the returns/forms mentioned above, shall be made <b>non-editable</b>. The GSTR-3B shall be filed henceforth with the system generated auto-populated values only in table 3.2.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>Further, in case any modification/amendment is required in the auto-populated values of Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B, then the same can be done through GSTR-1A for the same tax period. The values thus reported in GSTR-1A shall change the auto-populated values of table 3.2 in GSTR-3B instantly and the taxpayers can file their GSTR-3B with the updated values. Moreover, the amendment of such supplies can always be reported in Form GSTR-1/IFF filed for subsequent tax periods.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>To ensure that GSTR-3B is filed accurately with the correct values with no hassle of frequent amendments, it is advised to report the correct values in GSTR-1, GSTR-1A, or IFF. This will ensure the auto-populated values in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B are accurate and compliant with GST regulations.</p>
</li>

</ol>

<p><u><b>FAQ’s</b></u></p>
<ul> 
<li><p><b>What are the recent changes related to reporting supplies in Table 3.2?</b></p>
<p>Starting from the November 2025 tax period, the auto-populated values in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B for inter-state supplies made to unregistered persons, composition taxpayers, and UIN holders will be non-editable, and taxpayers will need to file their GSTR-3B with the system-generated auto-populated values only.</p></li>

<li> <p><b>How can I rectify values in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B if incorrect values have been auto-populated after November 2025 period onwards due to incorrect reporting of the same through GSTR-1?</b></p>
<p>If incorrect values are auto-populated in Table 3.2 after November 2025, then the taxpayers need to correct the values by making amendments through Form GSTR-1A for the same tax period. The values thus reported in GSTR-1A shall change the auto-populated values of table 3.2 in GSTR-3B instantly and the taxpayers can file their GSTR-3B with the updated values.</br>
Moreover, the amendment of such supplies can always be reported in Form GSTR-1/IFF filed for subsequent tax periods.</p></li>

<li><p><b>What should I do to ensure accurate reporting in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B?</b></p>
<p>Taxpayers should ensure that their supplies are reported correctly in their GSTR-1, GSTR-1A, or IFF. It is advised to review the draft GSTR-1 or GSTR-1A before filing so that any mistakes in the statement can be corrected therein. This will ensure that the accurate values are auto-populated in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B.</p></li>

<li><p><b>Till what time/date I can amend values furnished in GSTR-1 through Form GSTR-1A?</b></p>
<p>As there is no cut-off date for filing Form GSTR-1A before GSTR-3B which means Form GSTR-1A can be filed after filing Form GSTR-1 and till the time of filing Form GSTR-3B. Hence, any amendment required in auto-populated values of table 3.2, same can be carried out through Form GSTR-1A till the moment of filing GSTR-3B. For more details on filing of GSTR-1A please click <a href="https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/506">https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/506</a></p></li>
</ul>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/640</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] FAQs on GSTR -9/9C for FY 2024-25</title>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Additional list of Frequently Asked Question along with the response has been compiled in response to comment received from various channel. The additional FAQ dt 4-12-2025 is intended to further assist the Taxpayer in better understanding of various Tables of GSTR-9/9C and their key aspects - such as reporting of various values in Tables. FAQ can be accessed by 
<a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/gstr9_additonal_faq_04122025.pdf" target="blank">clicking here.</a></p>

Thanks, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/639</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Others] Gross and Net GST revenue collections for the month of Nov, 2025</title>
<description><![CDATA[<ul><p>Please click on the link below to view the gross and net GST revenue collections for the month of Nov, 2025.</p></ul>
<ul><p><a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/approved_monthly_gst_revenue_data_for_publishing_nov_2025_final.pdf" target="blank">https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/approved_monthly_gst_revenue_data_for_publishing_nov_2025_final.pdf</a></p></ul>

Thanks, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/638</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Registration] Advisory for Furnishing of Bank Account Details as per Rule 10A</title>
<description><![CDATA[
 
<p>Dear Taxpayers,</p>

<p>As per Rule 10A, taxpayers (except those registered under TCS, TDS, or suo-moto registrations) must furnish their bank account details within 30 days of grant of registration or before filing details of outward supplies in GSTR-1 or IFF, whichever is earlier.</p>

<p>The changes with respect to Rule 10A will be implemented on the GST Portal soon. Therefore, the taxpayers who have not yet furnished the bank account details till date are advised to update the same at the earliest to avoid suspension of their GST Registration and disruption of business activities.</p>

<p>Bank account details can be added through a non-core amendment by navigating to:<br>
<b>Services > Registration > Amendment of Registration Non-Core Fields.</b></p><br>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/637</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Others] Gross and Net GST revenue collections for the month of Oct, 2025</title>
<description><![CDATA[<ul><p>Please click on the link below to view the gross and net GST revenue collections for the month of Oct, 2025.</p></ul>
<ul><p><a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/net_revvenue_gst_oct_2025.pdf" target="blank">     https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/net_revvenue_gst_oct_2025.pdf</a></p></ul>

Thanks, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/636</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Registration] Advisory for Simplified GST Registration Scheme</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><b>Dear Taxpayers,</b></p>

<p>In pursuance of Rule 14A of the Central Goods and Services Tax (CGST) Rules, 2017, a <i>Simplified GST Registration Scheme</i> has been introduced to reduce the compliance burden and enhance the ease of doing business for small taxpayers.</p>

<p>As per Rule 14A (Option for taxpayers having a monthly output tax liability below the prescribed threshold limit), any person who, on his own assessment, feels that his total output tax liability on the supply of goods or services, or both, to registered persons will not exceed Rs.2.5 lakh per month (including CGST, SGST/UTGST, IGST, and Compensation Cess) shall be eligible to register under this scheme. However, a person registered under this rule in a State or Union Territory shall not be eligible to obtain another registration in the same State or Union Territory under this rule against the same PAN.</p>

<p><b>Key Features Implemented on the GST Portal:</b></p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• While applying for registration in FORM GST REG-01, applicants should select "Yes" under the <i>"Option for Registration under Rule 14A."</i></p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• Aadhaar authentication is mandatory for the Primary Authorized Signatory and at least one Promoter/Partner.</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• Registration shall be granted electronically within three working days from the date of generation of the Application Reference Number (ARN), subject to successful Aadhaar authentication.</p>

<p>Taxpayers opting for registration under Rule 14A are advised to take note of the following conditions, in case they intend to withdraw from the Scheme at a later stage:</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• All returns due from the effective date of registration up to the date of filing the withdrawal application must be filed.</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• The taxpayer must have filed:</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(a) Returns for a period of minimum three months, if applying for withdrawal before 1st April 2026, or</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(b) Returns for a period of minimum one tax period, if applying for withdrawal on or after 1st April 2026.</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• No amendment or cancellation application for registration availed under rule 14A should be pending.</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• No proceedings under Section 29 (cancellation of registration) for registration availed under rule 14A should be initiated or pending.</p>



Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/635</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Advisory : Introduction of Import of Goods details in IMS</title>
<description><![CDATA[
 
<ul><p>The Invoice Management System (IMS) was introduced on the GST portal from the October 2024 tax period. It enables recipient taxpayers to accept, reject, or keep pending their individual records uploaded by their suppliers through GSTR-1/1A/IFF.  To further enhance the taxpayer convenience, a new section for "Import of Goods" has been introduced in IMS wherein the Bill of Entry (BoE) filed by the taxpayer for import of goods including import from SEZ, will be made available in the IMS for taking allowed action on individual BoE. This functionality will be available from Oct-2025 period onwards. </p></ul>

<ul><p>It may be noted that, If no action is taken on an individual BoE, it will be treated as deemed accepted and based on the action taken, the GST Portal will generate the draft GSTR 2B for the recipient on 14th of subsequent month. Please <a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/creative_advisory_on_boe_in_ims_final_30th_october_2025.pdf" target="blank"> click here </a>to read the detailed advisory on the new changes.</p></ul>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/634</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Advisory to file pending returns before expiry of three years</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>As per the Finance Act,2023 (8 of 2023), dt. 31-03-2023, implemented w.e.f 01-10-2023 vide Notification No. 28/2023 – Central Tax dated 31th July, 2023, the taxpayers shall not be allowed file their GST returns after the expiry of a period of three years from the due date of furnishing the said return under Section 37 ( Outward Supply), Section 39 (payment of liability), Section 44 ( Annual Return) and Section 52 (Tax Collected at Source). These Sections cover GSTR-1, GSR-1A, GSTR 3B, GSTR-4, GSTR-5, GSTR-5A, GSTR-6, GSTR 7, GSTR 8 and GSTR 9 or 9C.</p>

<p>Hence, above mentioned returns will be barred for filing after the expiry of three years from the due date. The said restriction will be implemented on the GST portal from November 2025 Tax period which means any return whose due date was three years back or more and hasn’t been filed till November Tax period will be barred from Filling. In this regard an advisory was already issued by GSTN on 
<a href="https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/540 " target="blank"> 29th October, 2024.</a></p>
<p> Illustration : For ease of reference and better clarity, the latest GST returns that will be barred from filing w.e.f 1st December 2025 are detailed in the table below:
<table border="1">
        <tr>
		<td><b>GST Forms</b></td>
		<td><b> Barred Period (w.e.f. 1st December,2025)</b></td>
	</tr>
    <tr>
		<td>GSTR-1/IFF</td>
		<td>October-2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-1Q</td>
		<td>July-Sep 2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-3B/M</td>
		<td>October-2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-3BQ</td>
		<td>July-Sep 2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-4</td>
		<td>FY 2021-22</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-5</td>
		<td>October-2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-6</td>
		<td>October-2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-7</td>
		<td>October-2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-8</td>
		<td>October-2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-9/9C</td>
		<td>FY 2020-21</td>
	</tr>
</table>
</p>
<p>Hence, the taxpayers are once again advised to reconcile their records and file their GST Returns as soon as possible if not filed till now.</p>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/633</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Introduction of &quot;Pending&quot; Option for Credit Notes and declaration of Reversal amount in IMS</title>
<description><![CDATA[


<p>A new facility in the Invoice Management System (IMS) has been recently introduced on the GST portal wherein the taxpayers are allowed to keep credit notes as "Pending" for one tax period. Further, the IMS functionality have also been enhanced providing a flexibility to the taxpayers to modify their ITC reversal on acceptance of such credit notes thereby resolving many business disputes. In this regard please <a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/creative_faq_on_gstr9_for_24_25_dt_15_oct_25_v6_final.pdf" target="blank">click here </a> to go through some FAQs for a better understanding on the new facility. </p> 

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/631</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] FAQs on GSTR -9/9C for FY 2024-25</title>
<description><![CDATA[ 

<p>GSTR- 9/9C is now available to taxpayers for filing. A list of Frequently Asked Question along with the response has been compiled and is intended to assist the Taxpayer in better understanding of various Tables of GSTR-9/9C and their key aspects - such as reporting of various values in Tables. FAQ can be accessed by  <a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/faq_on_gstr9_for_24_25_dt_15_oct_25_v6_final.pdf" target="blank">clicking here</a> </p>


Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/630</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Advisory for GSTR 9/9C for FY 2024-25</title>
<description><![CDATA[
 
<p>Dear Taxpayer</p>

<p>GSTR-9/9C for FY 2024-25 has been enabled on the GST portal from 12th October 2025. Please ensure that all returns (GSTR 1 and GSTR 3B) for FY 2024-25 are filed to enable Tile of GSTR-9/9C. Further,  detailed FAQ will be published shortly for assisting the taxpayer in filing GSTR-9/9C.</p>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/629</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Attention : Important Advisory on IMS</title>
<description><![CDATA[
 
<p> It has come to notice that some posts are circulating incorrect information regarding changes in GST return filing from October 1, 2025. We would like to clarify the following: </p>

<p>I.    No Change in Auto-Population of ITC:
Input Tax Credit (ITC) will continue to auto-populate from GSTR-2B to GSTR-3B without any manual intervention. The mechanism of auto-population remains unchanged due to the implementation of the Invoice Management System (IMS).</p>

<p>II.   GSTR-2B Generation
<ul>
<li>    GSTR-2B will continue to be generated automatically on the 14th of every month, without any manual intervention by taxpayers or based on the actions taken by the taxpayers.
<li>    Taxpayers can take actions in IMS even after generation of GSTR-2B till filing of GSTR-3B and can regenerate GSTR-2B accordingly, if required.</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>III.  Credit Note Handling (Effective October 2025 period onward)
<ul>
<li>    Recipient taxpayers will have the option to keep a Credit Note or related document pending for a specified period.</li>
<li>    On acceptance of Credit Note or related document, the recipient will also have the flexibility to reduce ITC only to the extent of its availment by adjusting the reversal amount manually.</li>
</ul>
</p>


Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/628</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Others] Gross and Net GST revenue collections for the month of Sep, 2025</title>
<description><![CDATA[<ul><p>Please click on the link below to view the gross and net GST revenue collections for the month of September, 2025.</p></ul>
<ul><p><a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/approved_monthly_gst_data_for_publishing_sep_2025.pdf" target="blank">     https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/approved_monthly_gst_data_for_publishing_sep_2025.pdf</a></p></ul>

Thanks, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/627</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Invoice-wise Reporting Functionality in Form GSTR-7 on portal-reg</title>
<description><![CDATA[<ul><p><i>Vide Notification No. 09/2025 – Central Tax dated 11.02.2025, Form GSTR-7 was amended to enable capture of invoice-wise reporting of tax deducted at source (TDS).</i></p></ul>

<ul><p><i>In this regard, it is informed that the functionality for invoice-wise reporting in GSTR-7 has now been made operational on the GSTN portal. Hence from September 2025 tax period in Form GSTR-7 invoice level reporting is required.</i></p></ul>

<ul><p><i>Accordingly, all TDS Deductors are requested to prepare the data accordingly so that they could furnish invoice-level details on which TDS has been deducted while filing FORM GSTR-7 for the September return period onwards. Due date for September tax period return filing is  10th October 2025. </i></p></ul>

<ul><p>For any difficulty or concerns, it  is advised to raise a grievance through the Self-Service Portal available on the GST Portal, along with all relevant details, to facilitate prompt and effective resolution.</p></ul>


Regards, <br>
GSTN Team]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/626</link>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>