<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>GST News &amp; Updates</title>
<description><![CDATA[News and updates from the GST Portal]]></description>
<link>https://www.gst.gov.in/</link>
<item>
<pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Consolidated FAQs on GSTR -9/9C for FY 2024-25</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>GSTN has published series of FAQ on 16th Oct, 2025 and  4th Dec, 2025 for assisting the taxpayer in filing of Annual Return i.e., GSTR-9/9C.  For convenience, the taxpayer may access Consolidated FAQs by 
<a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/combined_faq_on_gstr_9_and_9c_17122025.pdf" target="blank"">clicking here</a>.</p>
 
Thanking you , <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/642</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Registration] Auto Suspension of GST Registration due to Non-Furnishing of Bank Account Details as per Rule 10A</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><b>Dear Taxpayers,</b></p>

<p>As per Rule 10A, taxpayers (except those registered under TCS, TDS, or Suo-moto registrations) must furnish their bank account details within 30 days of grant of registration or before filing details of outward supplies in GSTR-1 or IFF, whichever is earlier.</p>

<p>The following updates have been implemented on the GST Portal with respect to Rule 10A:</p>

<ul>
<li>Automatic Suspension:</br>
If a taxpayer fails to furnish bank account details within 30 days of registration, the system will automatically suspend the registration. The suspension order can be viewed at: Services > User Services > View Notices and Orders.</li>
</br>
<li>Adding Bank Account Details:</br>
Taxpayers can add bank account details through a non-core amendment by navigating to: Services > Registration > Amendment of Registration (Non-Core Fields).</li>
</br>
<li>Automatic Dropping of Cancellation Proceedings:</br>
Once bank account details are furnished, cancellation proceedings will be automatically dropped by the system.
</li>
</br>
<li>Manual Option to Drop Proceedings:</br>
If the cancellation proceedings are not dropped automatically on the same day after adding bank details, the taxpayer can manually initiate the process using the “Initiate Drop Proceedings” button available at: Services > User Services > View Notices and Orders > Initiate Drop Proceedings.</li>
</br>
<li>Exemptions:</br>
Furnishing bank account details is not mandatory for OIDAR and NRTP taxpayers. However, for OIDAR taxpayers who select “Representative Appointed in India” as ‘Yes’, furnishing bank account details is mandatory.
</li>
</ul></br>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/641</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Advisory on reporting values in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B</title>
<description><![CDATA[
 
<ol>
<li>
<p>Table 3.2 of Form GSTR-3B captures the inter-state supplies made to unregistered persons, composition taxpayers, and UIN holders out of the total supplies declared in Table 3.1 & 3.1.1 of GSTR-3B and is auto-populated from corresponding supplies declared in GSTR-1, GSTR-1A, and IFF in the requisite tables.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>It is to inform you that from <b>November-2025 tax period onwards</b>, value of supplies auto-populated in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B from the returns/forms mentioned above, shall be made <b>non-editable</b>. The GSTR-3B shall be filed henceforth with the system generated auto-populated values only in table 3.2.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>Further, in case any modification/amendment is required in the auto-populated values of Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B, then the same can be done through GSTR-1A for the same tax period. The values thus reported in GSTR-1A shall change the auto-populated values of table 3.2 in GSTR-3B instantly and the taxpayers can file their GSTR-3B with the updated values. Moreover, the amendment of such supplies can always be reported in Form GSTR-1/IFF filed for subsequent tax periods.</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>To ensure that GSTR-3B is filed accurately with the correct values with no hassle of frequent amendments, it is advised to report the correct values in GSTR-1, GSTR-1A, or IFF. This will ensure the auto-populated values in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B are accurate and compliant with GST regulations.</p>
</li>

</ol>

<p><u><b>FAQ’s</b></u></p>
<ul> 
<li><p><b>What are the recent changes related to reporting supplies in Table 3.2?</b></p>
<p>Starting from the November 2025 tax period, the auto-populated values in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B for inter-state supplies made to unregistered persons, composition taxpayers, and UIN holders will be non-editable, and taxpayers will need to file their GSTR-3B with the system-generated auto-populated values only.</p></li>

<li> <p><b>How can I rectify values in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B if incorrect values have been auto-populated after November 2025 period onwards due to incorrect reporting of the same through GSTR-1?</b></p>
<p>If incorrect values are auto-populated in Table 3.2 after November 2025, then the taxpayers need to correct the values by making amendments through Form GSTR-1A for the same tax period. The values thus reported in GSTR-1A shall change the auto-populated values of table 3.2 in GSTR-3B instantly and the taxpayers can file their GSTR-3B with the updated values.</br>
Moreover, the amendment of such supplies can always be reported in Form GSTR-1/IFF filed for subsequent tax periods.</p></li>

<li><p><b>What should I do to ensure accurate reporting in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B?</b></p>
<p>Taxpayers should ensure that their supplies are reported correctly in their GSTR-1, GSTR-1A, or IFF. It is advised to review the draft GSTR-1 or GSTR-1A before filing so that any mistakes in the statement can be corrected therein. This will ensure that the accurate values are auto-populated in Table 3.2 of GSTR-3B.</p></li>

<li><p><b>Till what time/date I can amend values furnished in GSTR-1 through Form GSTR-1A?</b></p>
<p>As there is no cut-off date for filing Form GSTR-1A before GSTR-3B which means Form GSTR-1A can be filed after filing Form GSTR-1 and till the time of filing Form GSTR-3B. Hence, any amendment required in auto-populated values of table 3.2, same can be carried out through Form GSTR-1A till the moment of filing GSTR-3B. For more details on filing of GSTR-1A please click <a href="https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/506">https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/506</a></p></li>
</ul>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/640</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] FAQs on GSTR -9/9C for FY 2024-25</title>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Additional list of Frequently Asked Question along with the response has been compiled in response to comment received from various channel. The additional FAQ dt 4-12-2025 is intended to further assist the Taxpayer in better understanding of various Tables of GSTR-9/9C and their key aspects - such as reporting of various values in Tables. FAQ can be accessed by 
<a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/gstr9_additonal_faq_04122025.pdf" target="blank">clicking here.</a></p>

Thanks, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/639</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Others] Gross and Net GST revenue collections for the month of Nov, 2025</title>
<description><![CDATA[<ul><p>Please click on the link below to view the gross and net GST revenue collections for the month of Nov, 2025.</p></ul>
<ul><p><a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/approved_monthly_gst_revenue_data_for_publishing_nov_2025_final.pdf" target="blank">https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/approved_monthly_gst_revenue_data_for_publishing_nov_2025_final.pdf</a></p></ul>

Thanks, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/638</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Registration] Advisory for Furnishing of Bank Account Details as per Rule 10A</title>
<description><![CDATA[
 
<p>Dear Taxpayers,</p>

<p>As per Rule 10A, taxpayers (except those registered under TCS, TDS, or suo-moto registrations) must furnish their bank account details within 30 days of grant of registration or before filing details of outward supplies in GSTR-1 or IFF, whichever is earlier.</p>

<p>The changes with respect to Rule 10A will be implemented on the GST Portal soon. Therefore, the taxpayers who have not yet furnished the bank account details till date are advised to update the same at the earliest to avoid suspension of their GST Registration and disruption of business activities.</p>

<p>Bank account details can be added through a non-core amendment by navigating to:<br>
<b>Services > Registration > Amendment of Registration Non-Core Fields.</b></p><br>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/637</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Others] Gross and Net GST revenue collections for the month of Oct, 2025</title>
<description><![CDATA[<ul><p>Please click on the link below to view the gross and net GST revenue collections for the month of Oct, 2025.</p></ul>
<ul><p><a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/net_revvenue_gst_oct_2025.pdf" target="blank">     https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/net_revvenue_gst_oct_2025.pdf</a></p></ul>

Thanks, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/636</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Registration] Advisory for Simplified GST Registration Scheme</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><b>Dear Taxpayers,</b></p>

<p>In pursuance of Rule 14A of the Central Goods and Services Tax (CGST) Rules, 2017, a <i>Simplified GST Registration Scheme</i> has been introduced to reduce the compliance burden and enhance the ease of doing business for small taxpayers.</p>

<p>As per Rule 14A (Option for taxpayers having a monthly output tax liability below the prescribed threshold limit), any person who, on his own assessment, feels that his total output tax liability on the supply of goods or services, or both, to registered persons will not exceed Rs.2.5 lakh per month (including CGST, SGST/UTGST, IGST, and Compensation Cess) shall be eligible to register under this scheme. However, a person registered under this rule in a State or Union Territory shall not be eligible to obtain another registration in the same State or Union Territory under this rule against the same PAN.</p>

<p><b>Key Features Implemented on the GST Portal:</b></p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• While applying for registration in FORM GST REG-01, applicants should select "Yes" under the <i>"Option for Registration under Rule 14A."</i></p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• Aadhaar authentication is mandatory for the Primary Authorized Signatory and at least one Promoter/Partner.</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• Registration shall be granted electronically within three working days from the date of generation of the Application Reference Number (ARN), subject to successful Aadhaar authentication.</p>

<p>Taxpayers opting for registration under Rule 14A are advised to take note of the following conditions, in case they intend to withdraw from the Scheme at a later stage:</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• All returns due from the effective date of registration up to the date of filing the withdrawal application must be filed.</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• The taxpayer must have filed:</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(a) Returns for a period of minimum three months, if applying for withdrawal before 1st April 2026, or</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(b) Returns for a period of minimum one tax period, if applying for withdrawal on or after 1st April 2026.</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• No amendment or cancellation application for registration availed under rule 14A should be pending.</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;• No proceedings under Section 29 (cancellation of registration) for registration availed under rule 14A should be initiated or pending.</p>



Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/635</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Advisory : Introduction of Import of Goods details in IMS</title>
<description><![CDATA[
 
<ul><p>The Invoice Management System (IMS) was introduced on the GST portal from the October 2024 tax period. It enables recipient taxpayers to accept, reject, or keep pending their individual records uploaded by their suppliers through GSTR-1/1A/IFF.  To further enhance the taxpayer convenience, a new section for "Import of Goods" has been introduced in IMS wherein the Bill of Entry (BoE) filed by the taxpayer for import of goods including import from SEZ, will be made available in the IMS for taking allowed action on individual BoE. This functionality will be available from Oct-2025 period onwards. </p></ul>

<ul><p>It may be noted that, If no action is taken on an individual BoE, it will be treated as deemed accepted and based on the action taken, the GST Portal will generate the draft GSTR 2B for the recipient on 14th of subsequent month. Please <a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/creative_advisory_on_boe_in_ims_final_30th_october_2025.pdf" target="blank"> click here </a>to read the detailed advisory on the new changes.</p></ul>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/634</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Advisory to file pending returns before expiry of three years</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>As per the Finance Act,2023 (8 of 2023), dt. 31-03-2023, implemented w.e.f 01-10-2023 vide Notification No. 28/2023 – Central Tax dated 31th July, 2023, the taxpayers shall not be allowed file their GST returns after the expiry of a period of three years from the due date of furnishing the said return under Section 37 ( Outward Supply), Section 39 (payment of liability), Section 44 ( Annual Return) and Section 52 (Tax Collected at Source). These Sections cover GSTR-1, GSR-1A, GSTR 3B, GSTR-4, GSTR-5, GSTR-5A, GSTR-6, GSTR 7, GSTR 8 and GSTR 9 or 9C.</p>

<p>Hence, above mentioned returns will be barred for filing after the expiry of three years from the due date. The said restriction will be implemented on the GST portal from November 2025 Tax period which means any return whose due date was three years back or more and hasn’t been filed till November Tax period will be barred from Filling. In this regard an advisory was already issued by GSTN on 
<a href="https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/540 " target="blank"> 29th October, 2024.</a></p>
<p> Illustration : For ease of reference and better clarity, the latest GST returns that will be barred from filing w.e.f 1st December 2025 are detailed in the table below:
<table border="1">
        <tr>
		<td><b>GST Forms</b></td>
		<td><b> Barred Period (w.e.f. 1st December,2025)</b></td>
	</tr>
    <tr>
		<td>GSTR-1/IFF</td>
		<td>October-2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-1Q</td>
		<td>July-Sep 2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-3B/M</td>
		<td>October-2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-3BQ</td>
		<td>July-Sep 2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-4</td>
		<td>FY 2021-22</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-5</td>
		<td>October-2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-6</td>
		<td>October-2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-7</td>
		<td>October-2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-8</td>
		<td>October-2022</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>GSTR-9/9C</td>
		<td>FY 2020-21</td>
	</tr>
</table>
</p>
<p>Hence, the taxpayers are once again advised to reconcile their records and file their GST Returns as soon as possible if not filed till now.</p>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/633</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Introduction of &quot;Pending&quot; Option for Credit Notes and declaration of Reversal amount in IMS</title>
<description><![CDATA[


<p>A new facility in the Invoice Management System (IMS) has been recently introduced on the GST portal wherein the taxpayers are allowed to keep credit notes as "Pending" for one tax period. Further, the IMS functionality have also been enhanced providing a flexibility to the taxpayers to modify their ITC reversal on acceptance of such credit notes thereby resolving many business disputes. In this regard please <a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/creative_faq_on_gstr9_for_24_25_dt_15_oct_25_v6_final.pdf" target="blank">click here </a> to go through some FAQs for a better understanding on the new facility. </p> 

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/631</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] FAQs on GSTR -9/9C for FY 2024-25</title>
<description><![CDATA[ 

<p>GSTR- 9/9C is now available to taxpayers for filing. A list of Frequently Asked Question along with the response has been compiled and is intended to assist the Taxpayer in better understanding of various Tables of GSTR-9/9C and their key aspects - such as reporting of various values in Tables. FAQ can be accessed by  <a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/faq_on_gstr9_for_24_25_dt_15_oct_25_v6_final.pdf" target="blank">clicking here</a> </p>


Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/630</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Advisory for GSTR 9/9C for FY 2024-25</title>
<description><![CDATA[
 
<p>Dear Taxpayer</p>

<p>GSTR-9/9C for FY 2024-25 has been enabled on the GST portal from 12th October 2025. Please ensure that all returns (GSTR 1 and GSTR 3B) for FY 2024-25 are filed to enable Tile of GSTR-9/9C. Further,  detailed FAQ will be published shortly for assisting the taxpayer in filing GSTR-9/9C.</p>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/629</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Attention : Important Advisory on IMS</title>
<description><![CDATA[
 
<p> It has come to notice that some posts are circulating incorrect information regarding changes in GST return filing from October 1, 2025. We would like to clarify the following: </p>

<p>I.    No Change in Auto-Population of ITC:
Input Tax Credit (ITC) will continue to auto-populate from GSTR-2B to GSTR-3B without any manual intervention. The mechanism of auto-population remains unchanged due to the implementation of the Invoice Management System (IMS).</p>

<p>II.   GSTR-2B Generation
<ul>
<li>    GSTR-2B will continue to be generated automatically on the 14th of every month, without any manual intervention by taxpayers or based on the actions taken by the taxpayers.
<li>    Taxpayers can take actions in IMS even after generation of GSTR-2B till filing of GSTR-3B and can regenerate GSTR-2B accordingly, if required.</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>III.  Credit Note Handling (Effective October 2025 period onward)
<ul>
<li>    Recipient taxpayers will have the option to keep a Credit Note or related document pending for a specified period.</li>
<li>    On acceptance of Credit Note or related document, the recipient will also have the flexibility to reduce ITC only to the extent of its availment by adjusting the reversal amount manually.</li>
</ul>
</p>


Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/628</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Others] Gross and Net GST revenue collections for the month of Sep, 2025</title>
<description><![CDATA[<ul><p>Please click on the link below to view the gross and net GST revenue collections for the month of September, 2025.</p></ul>
<ul><p><a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/approved_monthly_gst_data_for_publishing_sep_2025.pdf" target="blank">     https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/approved_monthly_gst_data_for_publishing_sep_2025.pdf</a></p></ul>

Thanks, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/627</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Invoice-wise Reporting Functionality in Form GSTR-7 on portal-reg</title>
<description><![CDATA[<ul><p><i>Vide Notification No. 09/2025 – Central Tax dated 11.02.2025, Form GSTR-7 was amended to enable capture of invoice-wise reporting of tax deducted at source (TDS).</i></p></ul>

<ul><p><i>In this regard, it is informed that the functionality for invoice-wise reporting in GSTR-7 has now been made operational on the GSTN portal. Hence from September 2025 tax period in Form GSTR-7 invoice level reporting is required.</i></p></ul>

<ul><p><i>Accordingly, all TDS Deductors are requested to prepare the data accordingly so that they could furnish invoice-level details on which TDS has been deducted while filing FORM GSTR-7 for the September return period onwards. Due date for September tax period return filing is  10th October 2025. </i></p></ul>

<ul><p>For any difficulty or concerns, it  is advised to raise a grievance through the Self-Service Portal available on the GST Portal, along with all relevant details, to facilitate prompt and effective resolution.</p></ul>


Regards, <br>
GSTN Team]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/626</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Advisory: New Changes in Invoice Management System (IMS)</title>
<description><![CDATA[
 
<p>This is to bring to your notice that several new changes have been introduced in the Invoice Management System (IMS) to simplify the taxation system and reduce the compliance burden on the taxpayers. The following are the key updates </p>

<p><b>Pending action for specified records:</b> Taxpayers can keep specified records pending for a limited time period. For monthly taxpayers, this period is one tax period (months), for quarterly taxpayers also it is one tax period (quarter) only. The specified records which can be kept pending in the system are mentioned below</p>


<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;a.	Credit notes, or upward amendment of Credit note </p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;b.	 Downward amendment of CN where original CN rejected</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;c.	Downward amendment of Invoice / DN only where original Invoice already accepted and 3B has been filed  </p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;d.	ECO-Document downward amendment only where original accepted, and 3B has been filed</p>

<p><b>Declaring ITC reduction amount: </b></p>

<p>It is clarified that, in cases where the recipient has not availed Input Tax Credit (ITC) in respect of the relevant invoice or document, no reversal of ITC shall be warranted. Further, in cases where ITC has been availed only partially, the obligation to reverse ITC shall be limited to the extent of such availment.</p>


<p>Therefore, In IMS a facility has been made available to taxpayers to declare the amount of ITC actually availed and, to the extent applicable, required to be reversed in respect of the selected record. The said facility permits reversal of ITC, either in full or in part, by entering the amount availed to be reversed. This facility may also be utilized in cases where the taxpayer has already effected such reversal, either wholly or partially, at an earlier point of time, or where the ITC pertaining to the relevant invoice or document was never availed.  Such facility is provided for the afore-mentioned specified records. </p>


<p><b>Option to save remarks:</b> Taxpayers can now save remarks while taking reject or pending action on records. This optional facility allows taxpayers to add remarks (will be rolled out shortly). Such remarks will be visible in GSTR-2B for future reference and to suppliers in the Outward Supplies view dashboard, to take corrective measures.</p>

<p><b>Important Dates:</b></p>

<p>The changes of keeping credit notes pending and declaring the ITC amount, as mentioned above shall be made effective on the portal from October tax period.  </p>

<p>Due date for keeping records pending: The due date for keeping records pending is calculated based on the date/ tax period in which such documents has been communicated by the supplier.</p>

<p><b>Prospective Application:</b></p>

<p>The new changes will be available only for records filed by suppliers after the production rollout of these changes. Taxpayers are advised to carefully review these changes before taking action and filing their returns.</p>

Thanking You, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/624</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Others] Gross and Net GST revenue collections for the month of Aug, 2025</title>
<description><![CDATA[<ul><p>Please click on the link below to view the gross and net GST revenue collections for the month of August, 2025.</p></ul>
<ul><p><a href="https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/approved_monthly_gst_data_for_publishing_aug_2025.pdf" target="blank">     https://tutorial.gst.gov.in/downloads/news/approved_monthly_gst_data_for_publishing_aug_2025.pdf</a></p></ul>

Thanks, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/622</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Refunds] Advisory –System Enhancement for Order-Based Refunds</title>
<description><![CDATA[<p>1. As per the available functionality, taxpayers could claim refunds under the category "On account of Assessment/Enforcement/Appeal/Revision/Any Other Order" (ASSORD) only if:</p>

<ul>• &nbsp;&nbsp; The cumulative amount of the Demand ID showed a negative balance (i.e., refund eligible).</ul>
<ul>• &nbsp;&nbsp; The status of the Demand ID was "Refund Due".</ul>

<p>This restriction prevented taxpayers from claiming refunds when individual components (minor heads) of a demand showed negative balances and the overall cumulative balance was zero or positive.</p>

<p>2. For the above scenario, several references have been made by the tax payers and tax officers stating that the taxpayers are not able to claim the refund. Accordingly the following changes have been implemented in the system:</p>

<ul>• &nbsp;&nbsp; Refunds can now be claimed irrespective of the Demand ID status.</ul>
<ul>• &nbsp;&nbsp; Refunds are allowed even when the cumulative balance is positive or zero, provided any minor head has a negative balance.</ul>
<ul>• &nbsp;&nbsp; Only negative balances will be auto-populated in the refund application (Form RFD-01); taxpayers cannot claim any refund for the positive amounts within the demand.</ul>
<ul>• &nbsp;&nbsp; <b>Order Number Suggestions:</b> The system automatically suggests the most recent demand order associated with a negative balance such as <i>order-in-original, rectification order or appellate order</i> etc.</ul>
<ul>• &nbsp;&nbsp; <b>Tooltips:</b> Clear guidance is provided near the <b>Order No.</b> and <b>Demand ID</b> fields to help taxpayers enter the correct details.</ul>

<p>3. A comprehensive user manual and FAQs will be shared shortly. In case of any discrepancies or system-related queries, a ticket may be raised with the GST helpdesk.</p>

Regards, <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/621</link>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<title>[Returns] Advisory on extension of GSTR-3B due date  in few districts of Maharashtra State</title>
<description><![CDATA[<ul><p>In view of the natural calamity caused by heavy rains, the due date of GSTR-3B for the July-2025 tax period has been extended from 20th August, 2025 to 27th August, 2025 for the following districts of Maharashtra state:</p></ul>

<ul>
                <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;1.Mumbai (City),</p>
                <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;2.Mumbai (sub-urban),</p>
        <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;3.Thane,</p>
                <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;4.Raigad</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;5.Palghar</p>
</ul>
<ul><p>For further details, please refer to <a href="https://taxinformation.cbic.gov.in/view-pdf/1010424/ENG/Notifications" target="blank">Notification No. 12/2025 – Central Tax dated 20th August, 2025 </a>issued by CBIC.</p></ul>

 
Thanking you , <br>
Team GSTN]]></description>
<link>https://services.gst.gov.in/services/advisoryandreleases/read/620</link>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>